<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page xmlns="http://tjansen.de/refPage" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://tjansen.de/refPage schemas/page.xsd ">
  <root>../</root>
  <title>The Jarfiller Story</title>   
   <embeddedStyle>
#contentDiv {margin-top: 20px; width: 1160px; margin-left:auto; margin-right:auto; }
#textDiv {width: 800px}
#textHead { font-size: 2em; font-weight: bold; margin: 1.5em 0 1em}
.textPara { margin-bottom: 1.5em}
#sigContainer { margin-left: 50%; text-align: center;}
#sigText { font-size: smaller }
   </embeddedStyle>
   
  <html><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" id="contentDiv">
<div id="textDiv">
<div id="textHead">The Jarfiller Story</div>
<div class="textPara">
I am a professional software developer for over 12 years now. Over those years
I worked at various companies, at many different projects, using so many different APIs and frameworks. 
And I don't know about you, but when I am not using an API or a language for a few months, I forget about
all the details. Even though they may come back quickly, it's hard to find a good reference as starting point.
</div> 
<div class="textPara">
That's why I started Jarfiller. It's a collection of references and tutorials for Java technology that get you started as quickly as possible.
Inspired by VisiBone's great <a href="http://javascript-reference.info/">Javascript Reference</a>, I try to
keep the tutorials short and try to be as concise as possible.
Instead of using many words, I use commented source code to show you how things work. Information that is not required for understanding the
concept is hidden in pop-ups or collapsed sections. At the end of most tutorials, there is a list of 'How-tos' to show you all
the details as well as solutions to some common tasks and answers to frequent questions. The result are documents that contain as much information
about a topic as many books do, in a far more concentrated form, but yet easier to understand than the API documentation.
</div>
<div class="textPara">
I hope that you enjoy Jarfiller as must as I enjoy creating this content for you.
</div>
<div id="sigContainer">
<object data="signature.svg" type="image/svg+xml" height="40" width="180"><img src="signature.png" height="40" width="180" alt="Tim Jansen (signature)" /></object>
<!--[if lte IE 8]><img src='/img/signature.png' width="40" height="180" alt="Tim Jansen (signature)"><![endif]-->
<!--[if gt IE 8]><img src='/img/signature.svg' width="40" height="180" alt="Tim Jansen (signature)"><![endif]-->
<!--[if !IE]> --><img src='/img/signature.svg' width="40" height="180" alt="Tim Jansen (signature)"/><!-- <![endif]-->
<div id="sigText">Tim Jansen</div> 
</div>
  </div>
  </div>
    </html>

  
</page>
